Guide to the Eugene Marshall Papers, 1839-1962
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Eugene Marshall papers 1839-1962
Marshall, Eugene, 1832-1919
Extent: 873 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Farmer, banker, and Union Cavalry officer, of Caledonia, Minn. Correspondence, diaries, writings, documents, record books, scrapbooks, clippings, and photos, chiefly relating to Marshall's military service with Brackett's Battalion, Minnesota Cavalry, in Kentucky, Tennessee, and Alabama (1862-1864) and on the Northwest Indian expedition (1864-1865). Diary includes comments on his immigration from Brockton, Mass., to Minnesota in 1853, and on secessionist spirit in Texas, 1859-1860. Letters from his sister reflect impact of immigrants on Brockton, 1890-1910. Includes material documenting aspects of the Dakota Territory in the 1860s; Plains Indians; Red River carts; the impact of the Civil War on southern unionists, middle Tennessee, and blacks; religion; education; the status of women; towns in southeastern New England, upper Middle West, Tennessee, and Mississippi River Valley; and Ignatius Donnelly, Horace Mann, and William T. Sherman.
marshall
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Papers of Eugene Marshall were acquired by Duke University in 1960-1962.
Biographical Note
Eugene Marshall (1832-1919), born in North Bridgewater (present day Brockton), Massachusetts, was a surveyor, farmer, and banker who served as a volunteer in the Union Army during the Civil War and Sioux Wars (1862-1865) while with units known successively as Curtis' Horse, the 5th Iowa Cavalry, and Brackett's Battalion. Marshall left his family home early and spent most of his adult civilian life in Minnesota and Iowa and his retirement years at Manchester, Tennessee. While on these migrations and during other travels in and out of uniform, he recorded a wealth of perceptive observations concerning the events, people, and environments in each area he encountered. Marshall amplified these passive observations with accounts of his own participation in politics and economic endeavors and commentary on national figures and events. His experiences in the Midwest and the South are complemented by equally observant letters from his sister who had remained in North Bridgewater.
Collection Overview
The Marshall papers contain a variety of material, but the most important and sizeable sources of information are his correspondence (1847-1918) and his diary (1851-1905). The diary, 35 small volumes and related materials, contains a considerable amount of information on Marshall's activities in the years 1851-1861 but is primarily devoted to his military service (1861-1866). An edited version of these years of the diary, The Civil and Indian War Diaries of Eugene Marshall, Minnesota Volunteer, a 1963 master's thesis by Clark G. Reynolds, may be found in this library. A typescript of a portion (1861, Nov. 20-1864, Mar. 14) of the war diary prepared by Marshall's daughter, Ethel, also forms part of the collection.
Marshall's correspondence, chiefly with his sister Olive (Mrs. Frederick L. Trow), provides a good amount of information for the antebellum and war years, but the letters are approximately twice as numerous and no less important for the period after the Civil War.
Another important portion of the collection is a roll of microfilm which contains copies of Marshall material at the Minnesota Historical Society. The contents of the roll are briefly outlined on cards in the main entry file. A more detailed summary may be found at the end of the current sketch.
Among other materials in the collection are: genealogical studies on the Marshall and related families (1588-ca. 1900); four volumes of records and scrapbooks (1852-1861, 1866-1883, 1906-1908); writings by Marshall, both printed and manuscript, including poetry, speeches, newspaper articles and letters to the editor, historical sketches, etc. (1855-1917); newspaper clippings, primarily dealing with his military service (1852-1914); business and legal documents (1855-1935); printed material, chiefly pertaining to veterans' reunions (1864-1915); pictures (1861-1913); and a small collection of miscellany. Stored separately from the body of the collection is one of the Indian arrows which wounded Marshall during the campaign of 1864. The arrow is kept in the library vault. Supplementary material to the collection includes: correspondence generated by Clark G. Reynolds and Anna Marshall Steer, Eugene's daughter, in 1961-1962; Xerographic copies of biographies of some of the individuals mentioned (filed with the first box of correspondence); and an article on George W. Northrup, Marshall's wartime friend (filed with writings).
There are some difficulties in using the collection which should be noted. The large number of volumes, etc., of the diary has necessitated the labeling of volumes. The diary also has several instances of overlaps and gaps. For example, three volumes contribute overlapping material for the years 1858-1860. Some rudimentary guides indicate the time coverage each volume provides. A guide to the chronological contents of the diaries is filed with them. This list correlates volume numbers with dates. In some instances wear on the pencil entries has rendered some pages nearly illegible. Some effort has been made to provide reconstruction of the entries. Diary entries after 1866 are few and scattered - clustered around and primarily concerned with the illnesses and deaths of Marshall's wife and eldest daughter.
A general recounting of Marshall's life and interests follows. Please see appropriate cards in the subject catalog for a complete list of dates and references for topics mentioned.
Marshall, after having failed to gain admission to Brown University, briefly tried teaching school in Marshfield, Mass. [letters], and then attempted to sell books on a subscription basis in Rhode Island [diary]. He attempted both ventures in 1851. Both turned out badly, and he left home for the upper Midwest in 1852. He survived the sinking of the Lake Erie steamer Atlantic, which had collided with the Ogdensburg, and made his way to Wisconsin, where he accepted a position as a schoolteacher while familiarizing himself with the opportunities available on the frontier in employment and enterprise [letters, diary, 1852].
In the spring of 1853 he wandered west through Wisconsin in search of suitable claims for farmland. He settled in Houston County, Minnesota, located on the Mississippi and in the extreme southeast corner of the state. In the fall of 1854, he was elected county surveyor, which provided him with an opportunity and an income to buy land. Marshall became involved in speculative schemes to develop the local economy until the depression of 1857 disrupted those plans. Hard times and ill health led him to journey to New Orleans and Galveston in the winter of 1859-1860 in search of a new locale and career, but he found both cities oversupplied with laborers. He returned to his Minnesota farm and became an active campaign worker for the Republican ticket in 1860.
Marshall enlisted in the Union Army in October, 1861, and attempted to obtain a position as an officer or noncommissioned officer, but he lacked sufficient political influence with Minnesota Governor Alexander Ramsey. He was mustered in as a private in one of several independent companies of Minnesota cavalry which later became a battalion within a regiment known as Curtis' Horse, later called the 5th Iowa Cavalry. This regiment served in Kentucky, Tennessee, and Alabama in 1862-1864. When in the winter of 1863-1864 Marshall and most of his comrades re-enlisted as a unit and went home on furlough, their Minnesota battalion was reassigned to duty with troops operating against the Sioux, who had been at war in the Northwest since 1862. Marshall, by now a sergeant in Brackett's Battalion of Minnesota Cavalry, took part in two expeditions in 1864-1865 along the Missouri River Valley into the Dakota Territory.
Medically discharged in January, 1866, as a result of wounds suffered while on the expedition of 1864, Marshall returned to his home in Caledonia, Minn., and married his fiancée, Elizabeth (Lizzie) Williams.
Marshall resumed farming in Minnesota briefly after the war, but in 1869 moved his family to Hancock County, Iowa, where he continued to farm and hold minor positions in local government. In 1880 he moved back to Caledonia and accepted a position in his brother-in-law's bank. Marshall retired from the bank in 1897 but remained an active member of the local board of education. In 1899, however, he moved to Manchester, Tennessee, with his two surviving daughters. Marshall remained in Tennessee, doing a little light farming and writing until his death in 1919.
The Civil War experiences of Marshall were not extremely eventful. For most of 1862 his regiment was assigned to the vicinity of Forts Heiman, Donelson, and Henry on the Kentucky-Tennessee border, patrolling against the operations of local guerrilla bands and garrisoning the area against occasional raids by C.S.A. Generals Forrest and Wheeler. Marshall occasionally was near enough to a major campaign to narrate operations on its periphery, describe its aftermath, or record rumors and stories of participants. Among the campaigns and battles so treated are the battles of Forts Henry and Donelson (Feb. 8, 1862), Clarksville, Tenn. (Sept. 5-10, 1862), Ft. Donelson (Aug. 23-25, 1862 and Feb. 3, 1863), and the Tullahoma, Chickamauga,and Chattanooga campaigns. The papers also give a glimpse of a long-range scouting raid led by Marshall's friend Northrup into western North Carolina in the winter of 1863-1864 as well as Marshall's critiques of campaigns in theaters far removed, such as those of Shiloh and Ball's Bluff.
Marshall's papers are more valuable sources on other aspects of the war for matters both inside and outside the army. He was particularly bitter and wrote often on how commissioned officers and NCOs were selected and how incompetents and alcoholics were able to retain such positions. The collection also contains a considerable amount of information about the following military topics of the Civil War: the cavalry, barracks and quarters (especially one transient billet at Nashville), camp life, mobilization and demobilization, discipline, firearms, food, foraging, medical and sanitary affairs, pay, recruiting and enlistments, supply, conscription, deserters, prisoners of war, legal rights of soldiers (notably whether they had the right to petition), and the procurement and care of horses for the army.
The diaries and letters contain many useful commentaries and descriptions of aspects of the war not immediately associated with military routine. There is a great deal of information on the condition of slaves, the affect of the war on Southern blacks, fears of slave insurrections, the confiscation of slaves, black refugees or contrabands, blacks serving with the Union Army, hints by the Confederate Army that returning blacks could enlist in the Southern armed forces and gain emancipation, emigration of blacks to the north, the prospects of obtaining suffrage in the postwar era, and the attitude of both Union soldiers and Southern whites towards blacks. Marshall comments on circumstantial evidence of miscegenation between neighboring households and in the case of a fugitive couple. There is also material on how the war affected women, white Southerners who found themselves refugees in the North, and Union sympathizers in North Carolina, Tennessee, Alabama, and other Southern and border areas. Marshall discusses some of the economic impact of the war, including confiscation of property by the Union army, smuggling, and the cotton trade in general. He notes the changes the war forced on life in cities as large as St. Louis and as small as villages in Tennessee and Alabama. Marshall optimistically commented on peace proposals as early as 1862, only to find himself still in the army three years later. While in uniform, he had opportunity to record his own reflections as well as those of comrades and other Minnesotans to the election of 1864, Lincoln's assassination, Johnston's surrender at the Bennett House in Durham, N.C., and the trial of Mary Surratt and her defense-by Reverdy Johnson. Among the Union commanders Marshall commented on were: Grant, W. T. Sherman, McClellan, Rosecrans, Fremont, Lew Wallace, George Crook, and Abner C. Harding.
The issues and causes of the Civil War were not abstractions for Marshall. During his trip south in 1859-1860, he encountered some of the feelings aroused by the John Brown Raid. Secession was discussed openly by Southerners as a real possibility. An associate of John Brown, Richard Realf, had left Texas for Washington to testify at a senatorial investigation just before Marshall arrived on the Gulf coast. Marshall found that the proslavery sentiment in Texas was so strong that its partisans had functionally suppressed liberty of speech, freedom of the press, and the local abolition movement. Texas' U.S. Senator Louis T. Wigfall openly advocated secession. Local laws on fugitive slaves were so restrictive that it was virtually impossible for free blacks to remain in the state. After the war, Marshall pondered what the proper policy for reconstruction should be, and he eventually had a chance to see how the South had evolved on matters such as race relations during his retirement in Tennessee.
Marshall saw only slightly more combat during the Indian wars than he had seen during the Civil War. The major action he participated in was the Battle of Killdeer Mt. (July 28, 1864), during which Marshall was wounded twice and the main Indian force dispersed. The expeditions gave Marshall a chance to record some detailed and valuable observations of the people who lived on the plains of the Missouri River Valley. His best descriptions are of the tribes living peacefully near army forts and former American Fur Company trading posts, such as the Hidatsa Sioux (or Gros Ventres of the Missouri) and the Mandan, and of the half-caste people who comprised the Red River Carters, who traded fur and buffalo meat and robes harvested while the Carters conducted long trains of two-wheeled vehicles across the north prairies. Other tribes mentioned include: the Arikara (Ree), Cheyenne, Chippewa, Crow, and Winnebago. Some Sioux tribes are listed under their precise names, such as the Yanktonai and Sihasapa (Blackfoot). Others have been cataloged simply as Sioux or Plains Indians. Marshall's observations of the Plains Indians include a description of their agricultural methods and how dogs were used as beasts of burden.
Most of the military concerns of the Civil War, particularly in regard to the quality of officers, carried over to the Sioux Wars. Others, however, took on particular importance. The problem of transportation of supplies and stores, especially forage for the horses, by wagon and steamboat, became the paramount concern as the army marched into present day Montana or into the northeast corner of the Dakota Territory over plains stripped of vegetation by plagues of locusts. Marshall also remarked on the service of U.S. Volunteers, regiments recruited largely from among Confederate prisoners of war for duty on the Indian frontiers. The regiments, prone to desertion and other disciplinary problems, constituted several of the garrisons in the area. Desertion and morale problems also arose among the Veteran Volunteers - the Union men who had re-enlisted - when the end of the Civil War did not end their service. Marshall noted the presence of a black scout accompanying the expedition as a translator of some Indian languages.
Marshall described the appearance, condition, etc., of several of the forts of the Northwest: Forts Snelling and Ridgely, Minn., which were respectively a mustering point and a winter's quarters, and Forts Berthold, Defiance, Rice, Sully, Thompson, and Union in Iowa and the Dakotas. Marshall mentions in passing two newspapers, The Northwest Indian Scout and The Frontier Scout, which were published at Forts Union and Rice. Robert W. Frazer's Forts of the West may prove helpful in locating some of these installations.
The expeditions went through few settled communities other than St. Peter, Minn., Sioux City, Iowa, and Yankton, Dakota Territory, which were the only towns Marshall described at any length. One of the secondary missions of the expeditions, however, was to explore and report on the Dakota Territory. Consequently, there is a good deal of description of the topography, vegetation, geology, natural resources, etc., of the countryside. Marshall repeatedly commented on the long seams of low-grade coal, or lignite, which lay exposed on the surface of the land, and which appeared to be burning spontaneously in one location. Reference should be made to the reports and addenda on these subjects found on the microfilm portion of this collection.
Marshall described and assessed at some length Gen. Alfred Sully, commander of the expeditions and son of the painter Thomas Sully, but said comparatively little of Sully's superior in the department, Gen. Henry H. Sibley. He discussed an investigation of Sully's conduct of the expeditions which arose from allegations made by Walter A. Burleigh, an Indian agent in and later a Congressional Delegate for the Dakota Territory, and territorial Governor Newton Edmunds, who was also a member of the Peace Commission negotiating with the Indians.
The Civil and Indian War material contains references to many regiments and other army units. Among the most prominently mentioned (in addition to those in which Marshall himself served) were the: 83d Ill. Inf., 6th and 7th Iowa Cav., 1st, 3d and 4th Minn. Inf., the 30th and 50th Wisc. Inf., and the 1st and 4th U.S. Vols.
The collection contains a great number of Marshall's opinions and observations on politics. He speaks of the rough-and-tumble ethics of the frontier politics of Wisconsin and Minnesota, maneuverings within the infant Republican Party in Minnesota [letters, diary, 1852-18601, as well as observations on politics in Alabama in the early l900s. Marshall himself only actively campaigned in support of Lincoln and the Republican ticket in 1860, but his papers also mention or comment on the presidential elections of 1856, 1864, and 1896. Some of Marshall's earliest diary entries include observations on the activities of Hungarian nationalist Louis Kossuth in the U.S. and disapproving commentary on eulogies inspired by the passing of Daniel Webster [1851-1852]. Political figures of note with whom Marshall came into contact include: U.S. Representative Cyrus Aldrich of Minnesota, who spoke on the same program with Marshall during the campaign of 1860; Ignatius Donnelly and James H. Baker, then Lt. Gov. and Sec. of State of Minnesota, and later leading figures in the Populist movement of the l890s, who spoke to the troops at Ft. Snelling while Marshall was there in 1861; Jefferson Kidder, then a Minnesota Assemblyman and later a Congressional Delegate from the Dakotas, was another of the speakers who visited Ft. Snelling in 1861; the southern Unionist politicians, Emerson Etheridge, once a Representative from Tennessee, and Anthony A. C. Rodgers, who would later be a Representative from Arkansas, both actively campaigned in support of Union-sponsored elections in Tennessee in 1862 and were guarded by Marshall's regiment; and Minnesota Governor and later U.S. Senator Alexander Ramsey, whom Marshall lobbied for a commission [all of these figures appear in diary entries]. Marshall's daughter, Anna, met Richard Hobson, naval hero of the Spanish-American War, during his campaign for a seat in Congress [letter, 1904]. During Marshall's military service, he commented frequently in letters and diary on the performance of Stephen Miller, Ramsey's successor as governor of Minnesota. He also recorded less extensive commentary on J. P. Altgeld, Governor of Illinois; Isham Harris, Confederate Governor of Tennessee; Henry Wise, Governor of Virginia, whose suppression of John Brown's abortive uprising triggered angry public demonstrations in St. Louis; U.S. Representative Jesse O. Norton of Illinois, who interceded in behalf of his son, an incompetent officer of Sully's staff; Zachariah Chandler and Morton Wilkinson, senators from Michigan and Minnesota, who appeared to be the source of wild rumors during the first year of the Civil War; and the difference of opinion between Senator Stephen A. Douglas of Illinois and Attorney General Jeremiah Black on the Kansas-Nebraska question. Marshall related an anecdote on how men of his regiment forcibly requisitioned food from George S. Houston, former U.S. Representative from Alabama. Marshall also recorded the comments of a fellow passenger of a Mississippi steamboat on Miguel Otero, Congressional Delegate from the Territory of New Mexico, and on the politics and government of that territory [diary, 1859].
Marshall wrote to and received replies from a number of congressmen and public officials [1894-1916]. Replies from Representative Mark H. Dunnell and Knute Nelson of Minnesota contain some specifics on issues and appointments. Representatives William C. Houston of Tennessee and James A. Tawney of Minnesota and Senators Cushman Davis of Minnesota and William B. Allison of Iowa supplied acknowledgments of a routine nature, although some of these letters deal with specific matters, such as constituent services on pensions, etc. Marcus Outright, the compiler of Confederate documents for the Official Records of the War of the Rebellion, replied to an historical inquiry, while the signature of Vespasian Warner, former Representative from Illinois, appears on a document above the title Commissioner of Pensions.
Marshall recorded his own and others opinions on various events of his time - the Trent affair, the reaction of the Democrats to the furor over Sherman's peace terms to Johnston, and the ability of women in Minnesota to exercise limited suffrage and office holding rights.